How long were, this is Humberj?
Huh?
The good looking one was Humberj?
Humberj was also good looking.
And the second one staying?
The second sore.
How long were they married before he was killed in the war?
Yeah, how long was married?
Came back from the army, it was in 1912.
It went in 1909 and it came back in 1912.
And he married, and in 1914 broke out of war.
Two years.
She gave birth to two children.
The first child was a girl, the second child was a boy.
And it was such a smart kid.
And it happened and the war broke out.
The boy got the measles and the boy died.
The boy died?
And the chanches, the sore chanches.
And you just remember?
Yitzchak's wife.
Oh, that's right.
That was his daughter?
That's right.
That was his daughter.
She was such a nice looking girl.
Yeah, she was a good looking, nice boy.
And then she got so fat.
She was, she was big but she wasn't really fat.
Who was this?
No.
Yitzchak's daughter.
They were cousins?
Yeah, cousins.
Wait, but how could she be his?
Sure she was cousins.
His daughter.
My brother's son, my brother's daughter got married.
And he had a entire two children before he got children.
And we saw his daughter when we were in Israel.
Hansha.
There was a...
We went to Haifa.
Haifa.
The tabaks.
Tabaks?
Oh, yes, a tabak.
Yeah, there were the few authentic tabaks that we met.
There was a handsome couple.
You took pictures of them.
We took pictures of them.
We have them in our books.
The dark couple.
They sort of looked a little bit alike, actually.
They were cousins.
I guess that's why.
That's what, that's what was confusing me.
They were cousins.
No, I didn't think they were sister Billy.
I figured they had to be really...
They looked a little bit alike.
No, he didn't.
But he did, really, as old as he was.
They were cousins.
Of course, they'd been married for many years.
Yes.
We must have such a nice little family.
And he was a man of school.
And he came back, and two years later, and...
By the way, he was the first victim in the world.
And mother didn't believe until she died.
She didn't believe.
She thought he was going to come home.
She thought it was a mistake.
She sent a soldier.
She said, oh, a Taniyish soldier.
And he saw a school of a fall.
He died.
He went to a rabbi in a difference in a town nearby.
And told the rabbi.
He died.
And he left our wife.
And he took children in Krasnobot.
And that rabbi sent a letter to the rabbi from our town.
But the rabbi didn't have the heart to tell.
He told certain people he told.
But my mother, he didn't tell.
And my mother, till the end, she taught me he's alive.
So how did she find out if the rabbi wouldn't have ever found out?
She didn't find out.
She didn't find out until she died.
Well, how long after that did she die?
She died at the end of the war.
Oh, I see.
At the end of the war, just when the Polish took over, they started to become independent
that time she died.
Anybody want?
I'm going to be asking you about your very, very earliest memories.
Thank you, everyone.
How far back do you remember? How far back I remember? I remember back when my brothers made
a little wagon for me. I was about two and a half years old. They took me for a ride to the mill,
you know. What kind of mill was it? A flour mill. But it was run by water. A big wheel was going
and the water was falling. This is my memory. Then I remember when I was three years old
and they took me to the Haida, you know, the Hebrew school. Hebrew school. In Europe, a child,
a Jewish, when they were three years old, they took him to Haida. Why? That's how he starts.
That's what he starts when he's three years old. And this I remember my older brother was
an assistant, I don't know how, a belfer, you call it. Assistant teacher? A belfer used to take the
children to Hebrew. He used to buy bagels for them and he used to get a bagel or two extra for what he
bought for the children. He used to give me. I was only three years old that time. And then I remember
when we moved in, I was also not more than three years old, we moved into Torbys parents. You were
only three then? I was only three years old because that time, you know, when they took my brother to
the army, it was in 99. And I was born in 93, I was six years old. Yeah, six years old. Yeah, I was six years old.
And I remember when my brother went to the army, when he came home, when he came home, he, he, he, you know,
I was the babe in the house. When he came in, he was, I was laying in bed, he came over right away to me,
the first, even before the mother, he ran over to me and started to kiss me.
Then I remember the wedding, what mama prepared for, his name was Schur.
And the people used to, the woman used to come over, he wasn't, when he went into the army, he was, he fell in
love with that woman. She was not nice looking, she was much older than him. And she had a scar on the face.
And he went away in the army at other girls. Nice, he used to send us pictures. And when he came back,
see, he didn't have no trade. They tried to teach him as a tailor and he, he could already, he was ready to
make pens. You know, he, he was half in, but he, he only liked horses. So when he came back from the army,
whole father, he used to have horses, wagons, used to bring people to other cities. So when he came home,
we gave him a pair of horses and a wagon. That was, that was the, uh,
dowry. The nodden. Huh? The dowry? The nodden. He, he, he, he, they called it the nodden.
It was like a dowry. I don't, I don't know how you call it here. They, they, you take a bride.
Yeah, you give something to them. He gives something, yeah. So they gave him that, uh, two horses and he used to.
So, but people came to tell mom, hi, hi, hi, you, you, you, let, uh,
I was such a nice looking, uh, boy, but, uh, so if she used to tell, I wouldn't sleep with her.
And, uh, she was as better as smart woman. And he got married and I remember exactly the
Vedic like it was like, right now. There was, was a Saturday. The Vedic started Friday and ended,
and ended Sunday in the afternoon. And they used to take home after the Makatuna, you know,
of Makatuna. The guests, they met music. They used to take him home. The music went through the whole
city, you know, to take everybody home. And from Tom Shevkane, mama's brother and, uh, and nephews and
nieces. It was a beautiful Vedic. They were, he was a wealthy, and father was a wealthy. Where was the
wedding held? The Vedic was held in Kassanwalt. In a, in a hall? In another, in Europe. In a house.
Whose house? In their house. They took harder for... The bride's house. The bride's house. They took harder
furniture. They left the empty room and had plenty of place to dance and then, and to, uh, and that.
This is the, uh, and then...
He, he, uh, used to take people to Samish, Tom Shevkane. And then he had, uh, a girl,
Hansha. And then I had a, a little boy. I, I forgot his name. He was such a cute baby. And smart. We used to go
through and she was standing by a window. And, and they used to see us outside even to, uh, then the
world broke out. And my brother, he, uh, it was foolish that time. A lot of people was murdered in him. And he,
they called the Razoifs and even right away to Samish and put him on a uniform. It was, uh, they called it the
Pudioska, Pult. And, uh, right away the Austrians approached to the, uh, it was not far away from the,
uh, from the border. And he was the first one to get killed. And, uh, that's how, uh, then they, uh, they
took us to ditch trenches. Because in Krasnabod, they made, uh, all around the city they made trenches.
And I was, uh, maybe, uh, maybe, uh, I was, uh, 13 years old that time. And I used to go,
work by the trenches. This is World War I. World War I. And this is the Polish government?
Not the Polish. The Russian government. And, uh, when they used to go for the pay,
used to be a Sunday they used to give the pay of, the pay. The, uh, Shkutze used to beat us up.
They also was working in the camp of pay, but they used to, uh, anti-Semitic, they used to beat us up.
And then, uh, they chased us out, they chased us out from the town in Viva.
Who, the townspeople chased you? No, the, uh, Russian government. The Russian government gave us an order
to, because this was supposed to be a battleground. And we run away by
a mile, a mile and a half in the city. And we stopped in the woods. We used to cook in the woods,
and eat in the woods, and sleep in the woods. And as the Germans approached,
I then once to see what's doing in the city, me and my brother's, uh, son.
And when we came, the city was empty, everything was closed. And I got so hungry, I felt I'd die.
There was no place where to buy anything. And they rushed back to the woods. And I found a piece
bread a soldier throw away. A piece, uh, how you call it? Black, uh, bread. I picked that up. That saved my life.
I felt so, uh, my brother's son wasn't. And I was so hungry. And then they came back, and they gave us an order to us,
to go further. And we, we hired a wagon from the peasants, and they took us to Samish. And Samish,
my mother had a nephew there. They took us in, in his house. And then, uh, a few days later, the Germans came in.
To Samish? To Samish. Everybody, everybody was running out to give him water and bread.
House, Wasser, Wasser, the, the, the lieutenant's, you know, that's how we... And I remember one,
one soldier from Tomshoff, he hired himself by my, uh, nephew. He walked out with his gun,
turned the other way, and he gave himself up. Then, then he became, he was before, he gave himself up. A couple
weeks before, he used to hold up Jewish people. He and another guy from Sochem, you know, the business
people. And then, then he came back to, he escaped from the, uh, uh, from the, uh, prisoner for camps. He
came home. They arrested him, the Jews, the Jews. As a crook. As a crook. And they put him in jail.
Then, uh, then, uh, then, uh, then, uh, then we came, then we came back from Samish after the Germans
occupied already Moslo. All Poland, uh, the, uh, the, the, the, the, the, the, the part of, uh, Russia.
We came back. We didn't have no house. So we also stayed outside in the woods.
But at night, he was, it was a Jewish people lived there. So we used to go up on the roof.
And how you call them? I bought them, uh, an attic, in the attic. He used to sleep in the attic.
Yes. Every Jew that then passed by, used to, then, up to sleep. So it was so dirty in the lads.
It was climbing up. I mean, they, the Jews would sleep in the attic?
Everybody who passed by, he, he was tired to let us go further. Then happened after attic to sleep.
And we were sleeping, the whole family. And we were cooking outside. Then finally.
Who did the attic belong to? Your mother's attic?
It belonged, no. It was in a village.
I see.
It belonged to a Jewish man. He used to live there for years. He was, uh,
but he did us a favor. We, uh, and then my, mama and my older brother went around to look for a house.
And they rented a house by peasants, which they renovated Russia. They were Russians. They were afraid
they were afraid of the remainder. They were afraid of the remainder. And they had, they had, they had, they had a little business in that house.
And they had a car scene, sold, sugar to the peasants to sell. The whiskey.
Where did you get the capital to buy these things?
I told you that Toby was a mate in Warsaw. She sent to my brother some money in Kalman.
That was the capital for the hat. And they used to go around and buy off butter and eggs. And he used to take it every morning to Zamish.
We used to get up two, three o'clock in the middle of midnight and we used to carry that to Zamish.
We used to come into Zamish for seven, eight o'clock in the morning. So we knew that where, who buys it. And then over there, we sold it back.
Our soul, sugar, paid back.
And that was day after day. And, and sometimes mother went home to, to sell to the peasants.
Sometimes my sister. Or my brother, my Schwager.
Until it moved in, the, the, the Jandars, the Austrian Jandars, moved right across, across that house.
And the, uh, sergeant, for such an antecedent.
Once a night, on a Friday night.
He had a mate, a Polish woman.
That Polish woman came into bar, pass, with my mother.
And, uh, my mother was kosher. She's gone.
Land apart, so she refused.
So they got mad.
And she told that sergeant, we still would, would, but then, he came in or not.
And, uh, and started to beat up my brother.
My mother started to holler.
Poor, it's, you know,
why you hitting me?
Look how much wood we have.
He didn't have to look.
Out the committee, he says, you, he want to hit her.
She says, I'm sick.
This out the committee, beschlap, like, yeah, leg angelike.
And, uh, and he walked away.
Then he had a knife.
My father went once to Krasnabur to the town.
And he brought, uh, a big, uh, gallon, uh,
was more, was, was about three, three, two, three or two gallons of whiskey.
And go on, go on, came home.
We already bought a dog.
You, you, you, was, was, hung there?
I don't remember how, what my father told him.
But he took out the cork and he smelled, he saw it's whiskey.
He broke it.
Then we saw that he can go on that way.
So we moved in another town, another town, in another village.
And that village was only Joomis.
For they lived in Poland for years.
They called them the Schwabs.
So we opened again, uh, uh, a little business for them.
They, so they used to come in that time.
Uh, a ruble was more, more avoided than the, the Austrian grounds.
So when they used to come in, Mama used to ask him,
what kind of money you gonna buy?
They said, rubles.
And then the, when it came, the yen she packed them and everything.
They took out crowns and paid.
So we, was a loss on everything.
He couldn't, he couldn't tell, you're a won that money because it was Austria.
So we, we had to, uh, move, we had to leave my brother then to Tomshof.
He had, uh, her parents lived in, and they got for them an apartment.
And we remained alone.
We moved in to Krasenbord.
Krasenbord was burned up.
But Toby's sister and another woman, and Yitha's sister, had together an apartment
with a few little children.
They took us in.
They did us, uh, my, my, my, my mama was sick.
They did us a favor to let us in.
And the children used to go, they used to go in the market to buy,
and they left the children, and the children used to,
cuckoo.
It was terrible.
And we couldn't stand it.
And Mama was sick, and my father was already old.
He couldn't do, he didn't feel also very well.
And money we didn't have.
So I went to Tomshof, Tzifis, you know, my foot.
And I was there, I met a, a cousin.
Mama's, Mama's, Mama's,
a daughter, Mama's sister's daughter lived in Tomshof, and they had a boy my age.
So he told me, he took me in, in a village very far away.
It was Mama's, uh, Mama's, uh, also, a sister's, a son.
And the father was, Mama's sister's, uh, husband was still alive.
And they went there, they treat us now, and they gave us some money.
And they went back to Tomshof.
And somebody with a sled took me back to Krasnabod, and I came to Krasnabod to hire
a man with a horse and wagon.
We pulled out whatever we had, and we went to Tomshof.
And we came to Tomshof.
Also, we, we didn't have where to go, but Mama's, a distant cousin, took us in.
The husband was in the, in the, in the, in the Russian army.
We didn't, we didn't know where he is.
And she took us in, and Mama was laying in bed sick.
And we didn't have a son, and the woman who took us in was also very poor, you know.
And, so, the only thing they told me, go over to that blunder, was a blunder, rich man, not far away.
Go into them, maybe they, I came in.
I was that time 14 years old.
I can't remember, what was the English?
I told him a story.
There was good, there were good nature's people.
I'm sure we haven't got there, what to eat.
We have no money.
So she gave me a half a brat.
She gave me some, I remember milk.
She gave me a whole, a whole bag met foot.
And she gave me some money else.
I came home, and we had already something to eat.
I think they gave us potatoes, you know, but, uh, yeah, already cooked, please call it me, potatoes.
And, uh, and then broke out an epidemic.
And, uh, it was a Russian, uh, Jewish doctor.
He was in the, uh, in the, uh, a prisoner of war by the Yostrins.
He used to wear his, uh, Russian custom.
And he used to go around, check the houses, whoever is sick and that, uh, and typhus,
whatever it was that time, the epidemic.
He used to put a sign outside, people shouldn't go in.
And he went over, came in in our house, and then over to Mama, she was, oh, he checked it.
She's, she's not, uh, epidemic, but she was swollen.
Toward that time, she's gonna die.
And he prescribed the medicine, and then later to the, uh,
apothec, you know, the...
You never done apothec.
Apothecary.
Hmm?
The drugist.
Drugist.
And we start to take the medicine and shmier, some of those.
And she came.
And she got better.
Meanwhile, while I used to go around and pick up by the business people,
but I assigned them to go to work.
So they didn't go to work.
They gave me a ruble or two croons, whatever it is, and I made up.
That's how we survived.
We, uh, and then we, uh, and Mama got better.
She started right away to do business.
Pushkar, food.
And, uh, that's how we, then we took her at our own apartment.
You know, nice house of Russians run away.
It was empty apartment.
My brother rented us at house.
And, uh, and it started to, uh, be normal already then.
Coleman, they took my brother, the German's cotton,
and they took him away for a fight someplace or something.
So when he came there, he was, he escaped.
And he came and stayed also with us already.
And then he went back to Krasnabrath.
They tried to catch him, to take him again.
And a policeman on a horse.
And Toby, she was, she was a tough one.
And she caught on by the horse.
And she didn't let.
The mane, the mane.
The hold the horse.
The harness.
And he, and he run away.
And he run away.
Wow, she certainly was brave.
She was, she used to be a brave woman.
She, he could have hurt her?
Huh?
He could have hurt her.
But, you know, a woman, uh,
that time had more respect for a woman.
And we started to, uh,
Mama got better.
We did business.
And that's all.
Turn around.
Until the war, the war finished.
That doctor then hum, you know,
the police, the prisoners of war.
And she got sick again.
She got sick.
I mean, uh, I used to call her,
it was a, uh, a, a, a, a, a doctor.
It was not a, a doctor.
It was a, a doctor.
It was a, a, a, a doctor.
It was a, I don't know how you call it here.
I knew the name how they call it here.
What did he do?
He prescribed medicines.
He was not a doctor.
A pharmacist?
He was not a pharmacist.
His son was a pharmacist.
But he was, he knew better than a doctor.
And, but he couldn't, uh, do anything for Mama till
she was laying from the beginning of, uh,
but she started that,
August, to get sick and till Christmas,
uh, Hanukkah.
That Christmas time she died.
She was 56 years.
And then, uh, we stayed together.
And, uh, uh,
we stayed together together in one room.
My father, my sister.
And then my sister got pregnant.
She had a baby.
And then she, uh,
her, she died in the middle of the night.
And, uh, then she moved,
uh, then she moved,
they made him to move out.
That house,
they moved him in a small,
a small room.
But she took in my father.
And then she went to the house.
I was already, uh,
working by a shoemaker.
And I slept there.
And I ate there.
And that went around till,
till they started to draft the Polish army.
So my brother Kalman got drafted
and they drafted Wolf.
First they drafted Kalman.
He was first.
And he came to Tom Shove.
He didn't want to go in the army.
He had already,
Libel was born that time.
He was a little child.
And I took him to the uncle of Oife
to make him something
that shouldn't draft him.
So that the uncle told him.
He, he always used to take out the teeth
not to go in the army.
They made himself a little blind.
They made him deaf.
But he says,
the best thing for you, he says,
you should drink, you should,
before you go in in the draft board,
eat a couple of herrings with vinegar.
And you run around.
Before you come in,
your heart is going to beat.
And they'll think you have a big heart.
And they might, they might not take you.
But then we went to Kazamish to,
Kazamish was the draft board.
When we came to Kazamish,
that was Friday in the afternoon.
The Tolan,
we didn't have no, also,
the money went out,
because we had to pay for the transportation
from Kazamish to Kazamish.
So we didn't have enough money to buy the
searing with the vinegar.
So we went from Kazamish.
Friday night, we went to Krasnabod.
We came to Krasnabod,
it was already about 10 o'clock at night.
Friday night.
We came into Torbett.
She gave him some money.
And all in the morning,
Saturday morning,
he had to be,
he had to be about 10 o'clock
in the draft board.
So we went right back
on foot.
They were working
early in the morning
through the woods there.
And I was like wolves.
I got so scared that time.
And finally we came into Zamesh.
Were they wolves?
Huh?
I don't know.
We didn't.
But the noise sound like wolves.
And we came into Zamesh,
and we then over to the draft board.
And he was running around.
And he came into the draft board.
And the doctors examined him,
the Polish doctors.
And they told him,
what kind of work do you do?
So he says,
he goes,
he didn't say he's a shoemaker.
He says he goes to the villages
to buy things,
you know, business.
So was there a Krasnabod from Krasnabod.
He had to send,
like,
like the mayor.
Over there they call him a soldier.
And that,
a Jewish,
a Jewish fellow says,
no, he's a shoemaker.
I said,
the doctor heard off,
he's a shoemaker.
So he'll be on the fresh air
as a soldier,
and he'll recover.
And they took him.
They took him.
He didn't,
he found,
I was staying downstairs.
I couldn't go out there.
So a bunch of Polish guys,
also,
they drafted him.
They came down.
I was wearing a Jewish hat,
you know,
they recognized me.
He says,
and they gave me a slap.
Such a,
like,
price fighter,
such a strong,
so I start to curse him.
He says,
oh,
you have to get it.
They want to come in
and slap me again,
but that could kill me.
Since then,
I decided not to wear
no more Jewish hats.
I used to wear a Polish,
and I looked like a shagat.
And since then,
nobody,
and he start,
he didn't want to go in the army,
so he was in Tomschev.
He was working there,
and I had to go
across the boat
to take care of it.
So,
for a little while,
and then...
So what did he do,
escape?
Is that it?
He ran away?
He didn't have to run
until,
if they draft him,
they still let him go home.
I see.
But then,
I don't know.
He,
even,
he went through so...
Kalman.
Kalman,
and even in Russia,
they stopped somewhere
on the way,
so he went down for,
to buy him bread,
and the train went away
with the family.
Oh, really?
And he had to go,
maybe about a hundred miles,
walking some beer,
to find,
to find him.
This was in World War II.
That was the
World War II.
And he found him.
He found him.
Amazing.
You know,
he didn't know,
but he was walking,
and walking,
and he found...
A hundred miles.
Maybe more than
hundred miles.
He got a hold of him.
He was,
he was,
he took chances.
Yeah.
And he took chances,
and he escaped,
with the Germans,
they took him to work.
He escaped twice,
and he escaped in the army
a couple times.
How old was he when he,
uh,
was walking in Siberia,
in World War II?
How old he was?
And then,
how old can it be?
He was,
uh,
in the 50s.
Really?
He was your middle brother?
He was,
he was,
my middle brother,
was Schleimer.
Kalman was,
which brother?
of that,
first was,
Kambayrsch,
then Schoel,
then Vigde,
then Schleimer,
then Kalman.
So Kalman was just older than you?
Huh?
Kalman was the next one older than you.
Six years old.
How many years older than you
was Kambayrsch?
Kambayrsch was older.
I'm sorry.
He must be older.
Kambayrsch,
when Kambayrsch's son got born
at the same time with,
with me.
We were...
So he was what,
18, 19 years older than you?
He must be,
he must be about 20,
21 years.
Because he was,
they're supposed to draft him
already in the army,
but somehow,
his visions was not so good,
that they gave him a blue billet in Europe,
in Europe,
when they took him in the army.
If you were very sick,
they gave you a white,
white billet, they call it.
Ticket.
They're never,
never going to take you,
even if a bull breaks out.
But if they give you a blue billet,
they re-examine you,
also,
only in the war time.
And a green billet,
there used to be a green billet also,
they released you this year,
they took you next year,
they called you again.
That was a green billet.
So, when,
when,
my brother's son was born,
he was already,
released in the army,
so,
it must,
he must be about 20,
21,
22 years old.
He,
yeah,
he finished with palmen.
So,
when,
when he,
when they caught him again,
and he escaped,
he came back to Tomshof,
fight himself.
And,
meanwhile,
I got tired to be in Krasnabod.
I was more used to Tomshof,
you know,
it's a bigger city,
I had a lot of mining company,
my,
so I went back,
when I went back,
they drafted Wolf.
I was,
mother,
that,
he,
he supposed to be drafted before,
somehow,
they didn't have this record.
For Wolf,
was born?
Oh, yeah,
Wolf was born in another city,
with my mother.
No,
and the father came from another city,
so,
and the children were born,
they put him on there.
Not in the,
where they were born.
So,
mother,
mother went,
way to come off,
and she took out,
at least 25 years.
That day,
he was,
uh,
21.
She made him,
that time,
for 27 years,
because they said,
the 27 years,
after the war will finish,
they'll be the first to release.
So,
that's how he went in the army,
at an older age,
than he was.
And they let,
they freed him first.
So,
I had to take care,
I had to take care on,
uh,
on Hagel.
And,
in Kalmy,
used to earn money,
used to send,
Krasnbrot.
Then,
uh,
in the war finished,
I start to,
I found somebody,
uh,
a partner,
they made partnership.
He was a krippel,
a lummer,
also shoemaker,
he used to go in the villages,
to work,
to work for the,
uh,
peasants,
to make him shoes,
repair shoes.
He was,
he was not,
lummer,
he was very,
big,
he speak the good Polish,
he was raised in a village,
that was Jeter's nephew.
Who,
who's Jeter?
Jeter was my,
sister,
my sister-in-law,
the,
woman,
which met,
saw her,
the scar.
We came in,
in the village,
and we,
found,
work,
by the peasants,
to make him shoes.
He,
for him was hard,
hard to,
to work.
We had to go,
to Krasnabod,
I had to go to Krasnabod,
to the Kermashemacher,
you know where the Kermashemacher minister?
I went,
it was in the summer,
it was already about three,
four o'clock,
I went to Krasnabod,
which was by,
mile and a half,
the open miles.
You know how much a mile is?
A kilometer.
Hmm?
I,
walked with the,
leather,
you know,
to the,
to the stitcher,
to stitch out,
I passed by a Jewish cemetery,
rather near,
near the town,
and it started to get accurate.
I got so scared,
I stepped on a piece of wood,
and it hit my foot,
I thought,
they grabbed me,
and,
how old were you then?
How old was I at that time?
I was,
about 16,
yeah,
about 16 years.
I was so scared,
I was,
it happened before the First World War,
Goyal,
from mine town,
from Krasnabod,
they used to go on,
on,
on markets,
all different cities,
to sell,
buy things,
while she,
when,
there she came home at night,
and she was sitting in the back of the wagon,
and she passed by the cemetery,
and she,
came home,
and there was,
at the colder,
from the cemetery,
and she was laying,
and she died,
so scared,
she probably got a heart attack,
and when I,
passed by,
when I passed by the cemetery,
I remind me,
about,
and I got so scared,
and I was,
but nearby,
they used to make,
pots,
from clay,
polish,
polish people,
that,
in the,
bake the,
the,
clay,
so I came closer to them,
closer,
got already,
I was not,
no more afraid,
but,
things,
like that,
I remember,
and then,
then I gave up that,
I didn't like it,
I didn't like to,
to eat,
but the,
they used to cook in our pots,
we took a long pot,
then I start to,
handle again,
me,
my brother son,
we used to come,
Krasnabur,
we bought meat,
and we took it to Tomaschow,
so we start out,
we,
they didn't have meat,
in Tomaschow?
They had,
but it was more expensive,
more expensive,
we used to buy,
in Krasnabur.
How far was Tomaschow,
from Krasnabur?
Three miles,
three open miles,
but the meat,
the Gulf,
in Krasnabur,
to Tomaschow,
or nothing,
nothing.
And we used to stay,
by Kalmanen,
because military,
and soon we woke up,
with packages,
the Polish,
and asked,
hold,
stay,
and we start to run,
why would they stop you?
Because not a lot.
You weren't alone?
Why not?
No, it's smuggling.
Was it smuggling?
Yeah.
To,
to buy,
from one town,
and sell it in another?
They're called,
they're called smuggling.
And if they catch it,
they take it away,
from us.
It cost a lot of money.
So we were running,
and they couldn't catch up with us.
Then we,
then we,
we came in,
in the wood,
for the Polish cemetery.
Usually,
for a Jewish cemetery,
I was afraid,
for a Polish cemetery,
we came to the cemetery,
and,
on,
on the gate,
we laid,
we laid down the packages,
and we rested,
and we,
that's how we used to go,
practically a couple,
times a week.
We used to bring,
a customer,
from Tom Schiff,
or something.
I remember that time,
what we took back.
And where would you sell the meat?
How?
In houses.
You just would walk,
from house to house?
Yeah.
They,
we had already customers,
to sell it.
And how much profit,
would you make?
I,
It was a,
it was a better profit,
than sitting down,
and working.
With shoes?
Yeah.
And that went around,
for quite a while,
and then I went back,
to work.
After,
it was already planned to meet,
and I went back to work.
I went back to work,
and I used to support,
her girl,
but her girl,
it was always,
something was the matter with her.
I,
couldn't,
wait for food.
And she supposed to bring me,
a pletsel,
with Miller,
until she,
get up,
and she take care,
and,
Harry,
baby.
And until she brought me,
where I was working,
the pletsel,
I got finger,
that's how I got,
ulcers,
from my gravation.
It bothered me.
I support her,
and everything,
and she,
then I got sick.
I was going to one doctor,
then I went to Jan Kaloroi,
and I went to a Polish doctor.
You had stomach pains?
Stomach pains.
And that,
another Polish doctor gave me a medicine,
and it stopped me.
But any time,
any time,
I got aggravated.
I came back,
even,
when I came to this country,
same thing.
I was,
came to this country,
and I start,
and I lived by,
my friends,
our brother,
just got married.
They took me in as a brother.
And they took me in,
I should eat it.
She wasn't a good cook.
And she cooked something,
she made hamburgers,
and she gave me the hamburgers,
I felt that raw.
And somehow,
I ate them,
and I start to get sick.
And,
just let me finish the story,
from,
the,
사,
the woman,
the pair shoes,
promised them,
Friday you're gonna have your shoes.
Friday night, she came,
before,
left benching,
she came in,
and,
who has my shoes?
Oh, oh, I'm gonna,
finish.
Took another three months.
And, peasants,
once,
in Europe,
by the,
the,
how do you call the,
the groom,
had to buy a pair of shoes for,
for the,
bride.
So,
big guy comes into,
you know,
from,
I need for my,
for my,
for my bride,
a pair of shoes,
next Sunday will be,
the wedding.
Could you do it,
or not?
Tell me.
So,
yes,
you come Friday,
you have your,
the,
the shag is coming in Friday,
no,
you're in a well.
He runs to the,
the,
you know,
the bottoms we used to make,
but tops,
come on,
a,
he says,
you know,
if I wouldn't have,
those shoes,
I'm gonna kill you.
I'm gonna,
he says in Polish,
if I'll hit you,
you're gonna,
use me plot.
He got scared,
he run away,
he was sitting there,
you come into,
do some other work.
He was afraid to come home.
He came home,
barna before,
left bench,
and came in,
and says,
Avrum,
you gotta make me those shoes
till left bench.
I told him,
how is it possible,
in an hour,
to make a pair of shoes?
I'm gonna help you.
And then I start to,
to work,
and I saw,
it start to get dark,
and we,
you know,
what we did,
I made him,
I made him in time,
but I fall apart
right after the wedding.
Why did they fall apart?
He tore off hills
from other shoes,
and he,
he slopped on.
So did he come back?
But,
after the wedding,
he brought,
he brought back the shoes,
fall apart.
I,
I took him apart,
and Marie made him.
And he brought,
a pack of potatoes,
he gave,
for that.
But he was such a,
he used to come in peasants,
he promised them,
that on three monasins,
that came in,
they wanted to kill him.
Why did he do that?
Was she gone?
I don't know why he did it.
He,
he didn't like to let out.
If somebody came,
he accepted.
And he didn't have enough people
to,
to do it.
Once our,
our,
our goyos,
I came in,
he says,
Joina,
if you're not gonna make me today
the shoes,
the boots,
thank you,
run away.
He was sitting also a half a day
by the kamashmacher.
Instead of sitting by the kamashmacher,
he couldn't do it himself,
make the shoes.
But he was a lazy guy,
he didn't like to work.
He used to come in and sit down
and sharpen his knife,
and run away,
and ride away,
grab the sharp knife.
I used it.
A lot of times,
I had to work
a whole day
and a whole night
because they said
they're not gonna go home
without,
without other boots.
Why did they go to him
for shoes
if he had his reputation?
He had a good reputation.
When he makes a pair of shoes,
it's not,
he gives good material,
good lettering.
This,
he was,
he was an honest man,
but he was a liar
just to accept.
My mother
ordered,
when I went in there,
I was not,
I was alone there.
And she came in,
you're in a pair of shoes for,
for her,
for her pair.
He accepted.
And she was running
and running around,
till I threatened him,
if you're not gonna make the shoes,
I'm gonna go away.
And he heard that.
for myself,
a pair of shoes.
He used to,
he used to have the leather,
he didn't buy the leather
by the kumash mark.
Some shoemakers,
poor shoemakers,
used to buy the leather
by the kumash mark.
He always had his own leather.
So he bought in
a few nice skins of leather.
And I saw that leather,
I said,
you know,
from that leather,
I want a pair of shoes
for myself.
Oh,
he couldn't refuse.
He,
then to the kumash mark,
I made a pair of leather,
bought a thumb.
I put away all the work,
you know,
I made my shoe,
hang them up on the wall,
till Passover.
He was so mad,
I says,
no,
his wife,
whatever he wanted
to make of her shoes.
He used to give,
before Passover,
day before Passover,
he used to give a shay,
a shay,
to take home,
to make the shoes home.
Because Passover,
you have to close a little shop.
He couldn't,
I used to give a ham,
a shay,
to make the shoes for the wife.
And then I went,
I went away from,
and I went to Krasnabod.
I went to,
a friend of mine,
got married,
and he invited me to the wedding.
So I came there,
and when I came to Krasnabod,
all the shoemakers were on,
and after me,
I should go back there.
So,
Tobiasa,
our brother,
he also was a very good shoemaker,
and he was rich.
From all the shoemakers in town,
he was rich,
he had his own house,
he had a car,
he came over,
a room,
come,
Get a car,
a cart?
A car,
a milk,
to have milk.
A cow,
a cow.
He came,
a woman come and work to me,
I'll give you any,
any amount.
And I was there,
I was there,
start to work,
and it was in the summertime,
silver o'clock,
he says,
a woman,
let's go bathing.
It was nearby a lake,
and you still pry,
to,
we,
try to match,
to swim.
He was a very strong man.
And I was working a little while there,
and I had a girlfriend,
she used to,
be a maid by the Lettnikis.
You know what Lettnikis is?
They come,
they come,
that was azota.
Summer visitors.
Summer,
summer.
They used to come,
rent a house,
by the peasants,
they used to have,
in the woods.
They used to have houses.
So they used to rent,
those Lettnikis,
and they used to move in,
in the stables.
And she used,
and my girlfriend,
she used to,
springs,
and bodhis,
and she used to wear,
fryer.
And,
and,
,
, and,
사,
and,
, and,
사,
and,
,
, and,
but,
before,
people,
and,
I,
I figure,
to dissolve the,
and,
that girl fell in love with me.
And,
she used to bring me every morning,
after the wedding,
but the wedding,
while we were at the wedding,
we were,
after...
Whose wedding was this?
It was my,
a friend of mine.
He,
that friend of mine,
was,
my Schleimuth was engaged to his sister.
So,
we were,
beside that,
we were very close,
but,
with,
with that,
girl,
that Schleimuth was,
was engaged.
I used to go out,
when I was,
12 years old.
She started early.
And,
that girl used to,
bring me every morning,
two blessings,
with Malach.
And,
she was,
crazy for me.
And,
then,
came Saturday,
and,
I had another,
Sfighat.
My God.
Also,
when I was young,
before the war broke out,
the first war broke out,
I,
came a girl from Tomchow.
her sister,
her sister adopted her.
She was an orphan.
And,
the sister was married,
in Krasnobot.
And,
I saw that girl.
She was,
dark,
reddish hair,
and such,
the color of this yellow.
her name,
a cutie,
a yellow,
in her grief.
And,
I fell lost on that,
that girl.
It came Saturday,
Friday,
I used to buy,
uh,
Tom,
can say,
candy,
and I bought the earrings.
And,
this is all the time
you were engaged to?
No,
that time,
that was a,
it was a kid that time.
A little kid.
And,
at the same time,
uh,
a few days before,
that girl come to the wedding.
She came,
was a celebration,
the,
you know,
uh,
when they finished,
they made,
uh,
the time,
they were a party.
Everybody,
the,
the shoe was burned up,
but,
then,
you know,
the,
was burned up,
but the,
the,
the walls,
were,
was still around.
I used to go.
And,
that girl came.
We were alive,
and I was 12 years old.
That time,
I was already 17 years old.
It was,
uh,
and we met,
and we were,
uh,
a whole night,
we were sitting,
and kissing,
and,
you know,
she came with another boy.
And,
uh,
and she thought,
that's it.
she was with a cousin,
from Tomshof.
She says,
I think you were already engaged.
That didn't,
she didn't remember,
if it's me,
or it's my brother's son.
He was also at that time.
So,
she couldn't,
I,
I denied.
And then,
I took her,
she was,
lived in a village.
I took her halfway,
home,
and,
uh,
suddenly,
me and another,
a friend of mine,
then,
to the village there,
we,
other,
other Jewish girl,
get together,
we were dancing,
and I go,
and finally,
everything,
got boyfriend,
she had a boyfriend,
but she didn't care for him,
from the village.
But,
at the end,
she married him.
But,
somehow,
when I saw him,
I got jealous,
and I didn't,
I stopped going.
I didn't go no more.
And,
then,
the next week,
that girl came,
to the wedding,
and she,
and she fell in love with me.
She was,
awesome.
She,
she would be here,
she would be on it.
So nice.
And,
uh,
before she left,
we made a party.
We,
bought a barrel of beer,
a small barrel of beer,
and cake,
and schnapps,
and she taught,
that we're making the party for her.
But,
the end,
she took me around,
kissed me,
and says,
how's gonna be our,
I said,
we're gonna separate,
and maybe,
I'll come,
to visit you,
to Kashabashin.
and,
uh,
she was waiting for me,
I promised her to come,
but I come back.
I came back home.
Uh,
your mother says,
she wants to break the engagement.
So,
we broke the engagement,
she went back.
she's like,